「良醫」前情回顧
Previously on "The Good Doctor"...
表現得像個普通人能有多難
How hard can it be to just act like a normal human being?
不
No!
你能別玩你那破兔子了嗎
Will you stop petting that stupid rabbit?!
我們再也不會回家了
We're never going home again.
我們有彼此  這就夠了
We have each other, and that's all we need.
你未婚夫的刀法不錯
Your fiancé sure can handle a knife.
他有著嚴重的缺陷
He's got a serious deficit.
你是驕傲還是失望
So, are you proud or disappointed?
馬庫斯  別摻雜個人情緒
Marcus, stop making everything so personal.
你打一開始就想要他這位置
You've wanted his job since day one.
在座各位都知道
Everyone in this room knows that.
-你怎麼  -我負責這個部門
- How did you... - It's my department.
我需要了解一切
It's my job to know everything.
既然我也為你工作
Since I work for you,
那這是不是都算你的錯
doesn't that make all this actually your fault?
不好意思  後面說什麼我沒聽到
Oh, I'm sorry. I stopped listening after "I work for you".
一個外科醫生需要懂得溝通
A surgeon needs to communicate.
莫菲醫生能做到嗎  重壓之下他可以嗎
Can Dr. Murphy do that? Can he do that under stress?
明知別人真的命懸一線時
Can he do that knowing that a human life
他能做到嗎
literally hangs in the balance?
我正在玩「無人之地」  但沒電了
So, I'm in the middle of "Uncharted", and I'm dead.
能借我幾個7號電池嗎
Can I borrow some triple A's?
我是你的鄰居
I'm your neighbor.
你好
Hello.
34號
34?
我上週搬來的  33號
I moved in last week. 33.
我知道
Yeah, I know.
我在醫院上班
I work at a hospital.
太酷了
That's cool.
是啊
Yes.
7號電池  拜託啦
Triple A's, por favor?
電池
Batteries.
對
Right.
你有嗎
Do you have any?
7號電池
Triple A batteries.
謝謝
Thank you.
給你個建議  別餵貓
Piece of advice -- don't feed the cat.
哪隻貓
Which cat?
你餵它一次  它就賴著不走了
Feed it once, and it'll never leave you alone.
謝謝你的電池  鄰居
Thank you for the batteries, neighbor.
不客氣
You're welcome!
外科
Surgical.
算你運氣好  我不是護士
Well, you're in luck because I'm not a nurse,
我是外科住院醫師
I'm a surgical resident.
有什麼事嗎
How can I help you?
找到跟查克匹配的肝源了
We got a liver for Chuck!
-在哪  -舊金山市立醫院
- Where? - SF Municipal Hospital!
肝臟從摘取到移植能存活多久
And how long do we have body-to-body on the liver transplant?
-八小時  -八小時
- Eight hours. - Eight hours.
你不知道肝臟的存活時間
You don't know the longevity of a liver?
這是教學型醫院  而我是老師
This is a teaching hospital, and I'm the teacher.
你和莫菲負責去取器官
You and Murphy, you're on organ pick-up.
檢查是否健康  把肝臟從舊金山市立醫院帶回來
Check the health and bring the liver back from SFM.
是我收治的查克  我真的很想
I was at Chuck's intake. I'd really like to be --
那你現在負責收治他的新肝臟
Now you're gonna be at the intake for his new liver.
傑瑞德  帶查克下來準備好
Jared, get Chuck down here and get him prepped.
肝臟只能存活八小時
We got eight hours on this thing,
時間不等人
and the clock starts ticking now.
良 醫 墨 非
第一季  第三集
本德爾醫生請到精神科病房
Dr. Bender to the mental ward, please.
本德爾醫生
Dr. Bender.
我沒有打擾你的術前準備吧
I'm not interrupting your pre-game, am I?
這是我的第四百臺乳房重建手術
I think this is my 400th breast reconstruction.
董事會真該送我塊牌匾
The board should give me a plaque.
怎麼了
What's up?
下午四點
Your 4:00 P.M.
VIP  萬納梅克
The V.I.P. -- Wannamaker.
對  器官移植
Yes! The Free-Flap.
他住進了頂層豪華套房  肯定住得很舒適
He's checked into the penthouse suite, resting comfortably I'm sure.
我給他做了一段時間的工作  他快答應了
I've been working on him for awhile now, and he's close.
他很快就要給基金會減免稅款了
He's real close to making the Foundation his tax relief.
太好了
That's good to hear.
我要手術萬無一失
I want aces on this.
一切順利
Everything perfect.
你這麼說太好了  我本打算通知的
That's good to know. I was gonna phone it in.
本德爾醫生請到精神科病房
Dr. Bender to the mental ward, please.
本德爾醫生
Dr. Bender.
這是主席版的鼓舞士氣嗎
Is this the chairman's version of a pep talk?
我在給手術上個保險
I'm looking for a fail-safe outcome on the procedure.
我想讓梅倫德斯醫生做你的助手
I want you to use Dr. Melendez as your second.
他就是你的「保險」  梅倫德斯
That's your fail-safe? Melendez?
我才是你的外科手術主任
I'm your Chief of Surgery.
這只是保障手術萬無一失的預防措施
It's just a precaution to guarantee a perfect outcome.
你在質疑我的能力嗎
Are you doubting my abilities?
萬納梅克很重要
Wannamaker is important.
一切必須萬無一失
Everything has to be perfect.
你已經說過了
You said that already.
我才是你的「保險」
I'm your fail-safe.
VIP病患不會有事的
The V.I.P. will be fine.
你沒事吧
How you doing?
我知道你可能受不了這些動靜
I know these sounds and everything might be a lot for you.
誰都難以承受
It's -- it's hard for anyone.
我喜歡直升機
I like helicopters.
我之前不知道你坐過直升機
I, uh, didn't know you'd been on a helicopter.
我沒坐過
I haven't.
存活倒數計時
到舊金山市立醫院要十五分鐘
15 minutes to San Francisco Municipal Hospital.
飛行應該很平穩
Should be a smooth ride.
你知道這算什麼吧
You do know what this is, right?
我來告訴你  這就是打雜
Well, I'll tell you what it is. It's scut work.
傑拉德運氣好  而我們只負責...
Jared gets the golden ticket, and we get...
送外賣披薩
pizza delivery.
螺旋槳一直那樣轉的  肖恩
The rotors just go round and round, Shaun.
不會變的
They don't change.
怎樣才能跟你說話呢
How do I talk to you?
查克  你有過胸痛氣短的狀況嗎
So, Chuck, any chest pains, shortness of breath?
沒有
No.
最近六個月內喝過酒嗎
Any alcohol in the last six months?
沒有
No.
-會疼一下  -四肢有腫脹感嗎
-Here comes a quick pinch. -Any swelling in your limbs?
這裡跟黑色星期五的沃爾瑪一樣
It's Walmart on Black Friday in here.
準備器官移植時就會這樣緊張
Things speed way up - when you're having a transplant.
我喜歡
I like it.
這是正能量
It's good energy.
那麼  沒有腫脹吧
So, that's a "No" on the swelling?
沒有
No.
我時常情緒低落
I feel lousy all the time, pretty much.
但是...我還能重新開始吧  有了這個肝
But...I've got a second chance, you know, with this liver.
當然
Sure.
見諒  我女兒的電話
Excuse me. It's my daughter.
我跟媽媽說過了
I already spoke to Mom.
還有湯米叔叔
A-And Uncle Tommy, too.
是啊  我得親眼看到你
Yeah, I need to see your face.
好的
All right.
我愛你
I love you.
再見
Bye.
她剛從加州的法學院畢業
She just graduated from law school at Cal.
我跟你說過
I told you that.
沒說過  恭喜
Uh, no. Congratulations.
那我應該是告訴布朗醫生了
I must've told Dr. Browne, then.
布朗醫生呢
Where is Dr. Browne?
存活倒數計時
肝源在這裡
Here's your liver.
需要你簽個字
I'm going to need you to sign for it.
標準工作流程是把肝留在捐獻者體內
Standard operating procedure is to leave the liver
in the safety of the body cavity.
我知道流程
I'm aware of the procedure.
本來移植名單上有個無名氏排在前面
We had a John Doe - at the top of the registry,
但還沒來得及移植那人就死了
but that John Doe died before we could plant.
你們摘取多久了
How long ago did you take it out?
三小時
Three hours.
我們一下少了三小時
We just lost three hours.
準確得說是三小時五分鐘
Technically three hours and five minutes.
冷藏箱上有準確時間
True clock is on the cooler.
不得低於攝氏4度或高於攝氏8度
Can't go below 39 degrees or above 47 degrees.
可以簽字了嗎
You want to sign for it?
組織看起來很健康
Tissue looks healthy.
你在幹什麼
What are you doing?
你在找什麼
What are you looking for?
-他幹嘛呢  -我不知道
-What's he doing? - I'm not sure.
門靜脈是八個肝段供血的主要來源
肖恩  你在找什麼
Shaun, what are you looking for?
腫塊還是囊腫
Masses? Cysts?
肝臟沒問題
They're clean.
你怕我們漏掉腫瘤嗎
You think we'd miss a tumor?
沒有問題
There's nothing there.
我知道
I know.
沒有問題
There's nothing there.
好了  得把肝臟放回冷藏箱
Okay, the liver needs to go back into cold storage,
我們該走了
and we got to go.
移植用人體器官
然後我放開血管鉗
...then I'll release the vascular clamp
讓你的血液灌注到移植肝臟裡
and let your blood perfuse in your donor liver.
-就行了嗎  -連上膽管
- That's it? - Connect the bile ducts,
縫合  然後靜候佳音
sew you up, and then we wait.
新器官都能適應嗎
Does the new one always take?
70%以上
Over 70% of the time.
那我就指望這個機率了
Oh, I can live with those odds.
你先休息
You get some rest.
待會見
See you later.
他盯著什麼東西  我不知道他在看什麼
He looks at something. I don't know what he's looking at.
他是...好奇嗎
Is he, you know, is -- is he curious?
他在擔心嗎  他從來不回答我
Is he concerned? He won't answer me.
你跟他交流有困難
You're having trouble communicating with him.
工作日裡的肖恩
It's a weekday. It's Shaun.
再看看吧  看起來問題不大
Hm, let's see. That seems about right.
他看起來跟在醫院裡不一樣
He seemed different at the hospital.
我在醫院裡還能跟他說上話
I could kind of talk to him.
他對醫院比較了解
Well, he knows what to expect in the hospital.
外界就完全不一樣了  到處都是新事物
Outside, everything's different. Everything's new.
新刺激
New stimuli.
那我該怎麼辦  我...
So, what do I do? I-I...
我不知道他在想什麼
I don't know what he's thinking.
克萊爾  你不會知道他在想什麼
Claire, you're not gonna figure out what he's thinking,
所以別試了
so don't even try.
其實  如果他在發呆思考
In fact, if he's thinking about something in his own mind,
那隨他去就行了
just let him be.
如果有人也這樣對我我會很感激的
I'd appreciate it if people gave me the same courtesy.
我想用您以前的...
I thought with your history --
克萊爾  如果你想跟他交流
Claire, if you want to connect with him,
你得找到自己的方法
you're gonna have to figure out your own way in.
查克怎麼樣了
How's Chuck?
查克嗎  他很好
Chuck? Chuck's fine.
他在等肝臟
He's waiting for a liver.
所以請趕快回來吧
So come home, please.
好的
Okay.
醫生
Doctor.
-什麼事  -我想跟你說聲謝謝
- What's up? - I just wanted to thank you.
我還什麼都沒做呢
I haven't done anything yet.
有的
You have.
你給了我父親希望
You've given my dad hope.
存活倒數計時
你知道嗎  查克是我的第一個病人
You know, Chuck was my first patient.
六個月前  我來聖何塞聖文德醫院的第一天
Six months ago, - first day at St. Bonaventure,
我就收治了一例肝功能衰竭
I get a liver failure.
他是這個世界上最好的人
And the nicest guy in the world.
我想由我來告訴他這個好消息
I wanted to be the one to give him the good news.
我們走不了了
We're not leaving.
你說過你喜歡直升機的
You said you liked helicopters.
我們走不了了
We are not leaving.
我們...我們安全抵達這裡了
We -- We made it here safe.
是的  但我們走不了了
Yes, we are not leaving.
我們走不了了
We're not leaving.
霧來的太快
Fog's rolling in too quick.
那霧會很快就過去嗎
Does that mean it rolls out quick?
有可能一小時  也有可能得三小時
Could be an hour. Could be three.
還不知道
Don't know.
好吧  我們得用別的方式回去了
Okay, uh... We're gonna need a new ride.
存活倒數計時
打擾一下
Excuse me!
我需要一輛救護車到聖何塞聖文德醫院
I need an ambulance to St. Bonaventure.
抱歉  現在沒有車有空搞送貨
Sorry. I just don't have the EMS.
80號州際公路發生連環車禍
I've got a pile-up on I-80
還有四輛車在外待命
and four other vehicles out on call.
一輛救護車都沒有嗎
Not one ambulance?
坦白講  這事很緊急
Let me be clear -- this is emergent.
一分一秒都耽擱不起
It's time sensitive.
親愛的  這裡不是租車行
Honey, this ain't Hertz.
警察護送呢
What about a police escort?
那倒是可以
That can be arranged.
當然
Of course.
我不想破壞現在的氛圍
Don't want to ruin the festivities.
但是我想和我的病人單獨待一會
But if I could just get a few minutes with my patient, alone.
萬納梅克先生
Mr. Wannamaker.
安德魯斯醫生
Dr. Andrews.
今天怎麼樣
How we doing today?
依舊還有個洞
Incomplete.
那看看有什麼辦法吧
Let's see what we can do about that.
看這裡
Look here.
鑒於腫瘤剛剛切除了不到兩週的時間
Well, looking not too bad considering we cut out a tumor
看起來還不錯
less than two weeks ago.
是啊  我一直帶著嘴邊的大洞到處逛
Yeah, I've been walking around with a hole in my mouth.
嘴邊帶洞喝威士忌試過沒有
Ever drink Scotch with a hole in your mouth?
著實浪費了好酒
Waste of good Scotch.
傷口需要一定時間來癒合
We needed to give it time to heal.
知道  知道  你說過了
Yeah, yeah. You told me.
你還抽菸嗎
Have you continued to smoke?
抽菸會收縮血管  癒合速度會變慢的
It constricts the vessels, slows the healing.
我不是個半途而廢的人
I'm not a quitter.
我們準備從你的腿上移植些皮膚
We are going to graft some skin from your leg
將你的臉頰修復得比原來還好
and fix that cheek up better than new.
我是搞房地產的
I'm a real estate guy.
有句老話說「下單要麼快
There's an old saying -- "You can have it fast.
要麼優質  要麼廉價  任選其二」
You can have it good. You can have it cheap. Pick two."
肯定不是廉價的
It's not gonna be cheap.
我喜歡你這樣的醫生
I like doctors like you.
你很厲害  你自己也知道的
You're good, and you know it.
存活倒數計時
是的  在我們來之前就已經摘取了
Yes. It was harvested before we got there.
我們正等車送我們回去
We're waiting for transportation.
行程和存活時間都有所改變
The itinerary and the life clock have changed.
是的...現在還剩4小時14分鐘
Yeah, uh... Four hours and 14 minutes.
打擾一下  你是在和醫院通話嗎
Excuse me! Are you talking to the hospital?
麻煩找人轉告一下格拉斯曼醫生
Have someone tell - Dr. Glassman
我們的午餐  我可能得遲到
that I might be late for our lunch, please.
是
Yeah.
好的
Okay.
所以你是怎麼預知天氣的
So, how did you know about the weather?
是某種天賦嗎
Is it some kind of gift?
拜託  我想知道
Come on, I got to know.
什麼  肖恩·莫菲是宙斯嗎
What, Shaun Murphy is Zeus?
我看了天氣預報
I watch The Weather Channel.
你們是我要接的醫生
You my doctors?
肖恩
Shaun?
肖恩  我們得走了
Shaun, we got to go!
你到家了
You're home.
因為你弟弟的事  你爸媽今晚都不太好受
Your dad and mom have had a tough night with your brother and all.
快  走吧
Come on. Let's go.
不要  不要
No! No!
他...他答應過我的
He -- He promised me!
He...He promised me!
他答應了的  他答應過我的
He promised! He promised me!
他答應我的  他答應我的
He promised me! He promised me!
我覺得開車的話會更快到達  肖恩
I think we'll get there much quicker if we drive, Shaun.
能麻煩你把警燈關了嗎
C-Could you turn off the flashers, please?
患者的姓名是什麼
What's the patient's name?
我告訴過你了  是查克
I told you. It's Chuck.
-不是  -不是
- No. - No?
不是  器官捐獻者的名字
No. The -- The donor?
他的名字是什麼
What's his name?
什麼  肝臟嗎
What? The liver?
我...
I...
「奧利佛」
"Oliver"?
奧利佛
Oliver.
你有空嗎
Hey, you got a second?
怎麼了
What's up?
在等一個肝源
Just waiting on a liver.
移植手術  人人都想參與
Transplant. Everyone wants in.
大家寧願用自己的肝換取參與手術的機會
They'd trade their liver to do the liver.
話說  你的自由皮瓣移植需要幫忙嗎
Hey, look, uh, you want some help on this Free-Flap?
他叫什麼來著
What's his name?
萬納梅克
Wannamaker.
你有移植手術要做
You got the transplant.
應該讓任何主治醫生都忙得不可開交才對
That should keep any attending busy.
我可以擠時間
Well, I can make time.
青木來找過你了
Aoki come to you about this?
聽著  我知道  你是主任
Look, I get it. You're the Chief.
沒錯
That's right.
聽著  這不是政治陰謀
Look, this -- this isn't a coup.
那是什麼
What is it?
是為了確保我們的醫院
It's about making sure this hospital is first
排在萬納梅克的捐款名單首位
on Wannamaker's donation list.
利害關係我清楚得很
I'm aware of the stakes.
多謝你過來告訴我
Thanks for coming by.
你知道的  讓我做你的助手
You know, it doesn't make you any less of a surgeon,
對你沒有任何壞處
having me in there as your second.
我是你的主任  你是我的主治醫師
I'm the Chief. You're my attending.
說得沒錯
Can't argue with that.
你我都清楚你出現在我的手術室裡意味著什麼
And we both know what your presence in my O.R. will say.
那並不是我的本意
That's not my intention.
重要的是產生的影響  意圖不重要
It's the impact. Intention doesn't matter.
謝了  但是我不需要
Thanks...but I'm good.
這結果不對
These can't be right.
不管這是哪份報告  結果肯定沒問題
Whatever it is, it's right.
查克的化驗結果
Chuck's labs.
不是弄錯了人就是檢查結果有誤
It's got to be a false flag or a bad reading.
怎麼會
For what?
藥物  或是食物  我不知道
Medications? Foods? I don't know.
如果結果沒錯  我們就沒辦法移植了
Look, if this is right, we lose our transplant.
我很抱歉  但結果就是這樣
I'm sorry. That doesn't change the results.
他體內有酒精
There's alcohol in his system.
他喝酒了
He drank.
血液不會撒謊
The blood doesn't lie.
重做一遍化驗
Run the lab again.
存活倒數計時
到聖何塞聖文德醫院要多久
E.T.A. To St. Bonaventure?
70分鐘
70 minutes.
你在找什麼
What are you looking for?
你看到什麼了
What do you see?
我有個女鄰居
I have a girl neighbor.
好吧
Okay.
她人好嗎
Is she nice?
她做什麼工作的  有男朋友嗎
What does she do? - Does she...have a boyfriend?
你知道她叫什麼嗎
Do you know her name?
你到底在片子上找什麼呢
What the hell are you looking for on the scans?
你到底在
What the...
溫度在升高
The temperature is going up!
警官  我們得找個有冰的地方  馬上
Officer, we need to find a place with ice, like, now!
我給你做了化驗  查克  而且化驗了兩遍
I tested it, Chuck. And re-tested it.
說話啊  你知道六個月內不能喝酒的規矩
Talk to me. You know the six-month rule.
-是忍不住嗎  -是三天前
- Was it a craving? - It was three days ago.
我女兒的畢業典禮
My daughter's graduation.
我們家裡沒有人上過大學
Nobody in my family had ever gone to college.
她就站在那
There she was.
我的寶貝女兒穿著學士服
My little girl wearing the robes.
在那天  我只想做個平凡的父親
And for just that day, I...I wanted to be normal.
所以  我喝了一杯香檳
So, I...I had a glass of champagne.
存活倒數計時
你們沒有冰了
You're out of ice?
冰箱壞了  五公里外有個超市
It's broken. Supermarket's about three miles down.
我們沒時間了
We don't have time.
好吧  好吧
Okay. Okay.
溫度已經到攝氏8度了
The temperature's already at 47 degrees.
我們不能讓它再繼續升高了
We can't let it go any higher.
你不來幫我嗎
Are you gonna help me?
這是甜的  你會喜歡的
It's sweet. You'll like it.
我們該拿他怎麼辦
What should I do with him?
兒童保護機構在夏延
Child Services is down in Cheyenne.
到那有240公里  他們肯定會把我打發回來
That's 150 miles, and they'll just turn me around
讓我送到他父母那裡
and send me back to the parents.
他父母不想要他嗎
The parents don't want him?
不知道
I don't know.
他不想和父母在一起  這是肯定的
He doesn't seem to want the parents, that's for sure.
你可以帶他去醫院
You can take him to do the hospital.
那有社工
Social worker there.
那樣不管用
That won't work.
你怎麼知道
How do you know?
肖恩
Shaun?
你說得對  不管用  為什麼
You're right. It's not working! Why?
肖恩
Shaun!
你到底有沒有在聽我說話
Are you even listening to me?!
只喝了一杯
Just one drink?
他是這麼說的
That's what he said.
要不要通知器官移植登記中心
Should I inform the registry?
查克多長時間以前喝的那杯酒
How long ago - did Chuck have that drink?
三天前
Three days ago.
把馬克筆給我
Give me your marker.
這是
That's...
血液酒精含量估計值
Estimated blood-alcohol content.
他喝的是什麼酒
What type of alcohol?
香檳
Uh, champagne.
酒精含量是多少
What percentage of alcohol is that?
我不知道  有什麼關係嗎
I don't know. What's the difference?
把手機拿出來查查
Take out your phone and look it up.
我不知道為什麼它不管用
I don't know why it's not working!
要被冰水淹沒才可以
It needs to be submerged to cool.
五秒鐘就是好幾升
Every five seconds is an XL.
為什麼最後一次你回答我了  之前卻不回答
Why did you answer me the last time, but not before?
是因為我生氣了嗎
Was it because I was angry?
是巧合嗎
Was it random?
為什麼你就不能回答我的問題
Why can't you answer my questions?
這樣好多了
This better work.
會管用的
It will work.
我不問的時候你就會說
You answer when I don't ask.
你不喜歡問題
You don't like questions.
不喜歡
I don't.
我微積分沒學好
I didn't do well in calculus.
這是代數
This is algebra.
他有重度肝硬化
With his severe cirrhosis,
酒精清除率為每小時每分一毫克升
his alcohol-clearance rate is one milligram per deciliter per hour.
一杯酒  就算八盎司
One drink, say eight ounces...
他喝的香檳  最多六盎司
If it's champagne, six ounces, tops.
留出餘量來
Play it conservative.
八盎司換算成血液酒精濃度
Eight ounces results in a blood alcohol level
就是每分39毫克升
of 39 milligrams per deciliter.
一單位酒精量
One standard drink.
禁酒的目的
Now, the purpose of abstinence,
至少根據移植中心來說...
at least according to the transplant registry is...
過量飲酒導致肝臟受損的患者
Patients who kill their livers due to excessive drinking
證明自己可保持清醒
prove they can be sober.
給我看一下報告
Let me see that report.
0.02
查克說的是實話
Chuck was telling the truth.
他確實只喝了一杯
He did have just the one drink.
他的酒癮沒有復發
He didn't fall off the wagon.
董事會肯定喜歡這個情況
Corporate loves its data.
我不確定這是否有用
I'm not sure it'll actually make a difference,
但至少給了我們機會
but it does give us an argument.
你是個天才
You are a genius.
你不喜歡食堂的飯菜嗎
You don't like the cafeteria food?
他們只能做好一件
They only make one thing well.
要是員工看見他們的院長
What does it say when the staff sees
沒有吃食堂的飯菜會怎麼想
the President of the hospital not eating their cafeteria food?
這說明院長
Well, it says the President of the hospital
不允許進廚房
isn't allowed in the kitchen.
你坐下了  我能為你做什麼
You sat down. What can I do for you?
我想聽聽你的建議
I'd like your advice.
是嗎
Really?
青木呢  她去世了嗎
Where's Aoki? Did she die?
這真是個錯誤
This was a mistake.
太無禮了  坐下吧
That's insulting. Sit down.
至少聽完我要說什麼
At least hear what I have to say,
再決定這是個壞主意
and then decide it's bad advice.
坐吧
Sit.
青木把梅倫德斯推給我  去做VIP的手術
Aoki is pushing Melendez on me for the VIP.
你沒收到群發的郵件
You didn't get the e-mail blast.
有錢人不能死在這家醫院裡
Rich people aren't allowed to die in this hospital.
你不再是明日之星了
You're not the young star anymore.
梅倫德斯才是
Melendez is.
我知道
I know that.
那你還對「為什麼」而苦惱嗎
And you're upset about the "Why"?
為什麼青木這麼想
Why does Aoki think that?
你應該問的是「誰」
You should be asking "Who".
「誰」  我知道是誰  梅倫德斯
"Who"? I know who. Melendez.
你是「誰」
Who are you?
你是想當頂級外科醫生的主任
Are you a Chief who wants to be top surgeon,
還是個想當院長的主任
or are you a Chief who wants to be president?
因為若是後者  就撿起你的自我
'Cause if it's the latter, take your ego,
塞進什麼碗櫃裡
shove it in a cupboard somewhere,
表現得像個院長的樣子
and start acting presidential.
梅倫德斯醫生會和董事會溝通
Dr. Melendez is going to argue to the board
讓你移植這個肝臟
that you get this liver.
我認為勝算很大
And I think it's a pretty good argument.
我值得嗎
Do I deserve it?
我認為這與此無關
I'm... not sure that's relevant.
你知道嗎
You know...
當人瀕死時
when you're dying,
而我已經瀕死很久了
and I've been dying for a long time,
你會開始思考自己的人生
you start to think about your life.
我過得不如人意
I haven't led a great one.
我本該成為一個更好的父親
I could've been a better dad.
更好的男人
A better man.
告訴你  我曾酗酒
News flash, I drank too much.
你知道嗎  我還有個兒子
You know, I also have a son.
第一次婚姻時生的
Yeah. First marriage.
我有三年沒見過他了
I haven't seen him in three years.
肝臟移植不是你的第二次機會
Getting a liver is not a second chance,
也不是給好人的獎勵
and it's not a reward for being perfect.
只是我們能做的
It's just what we can do.
也許吧
Maybe.
但在移植登記系統裡
But on the registry,
我們所有人都排著隊
all of us wait in line together.
而我看到...
And I see these ...
看到這些人等著
these people here, waiting.
我認識他們的臉
I know their faces.
甚至知道他們的名字
Even their names.
他們都有各自的故事
They all have stories.
而我們一起排在上面
We're in it together.
而我...
And I...
我打破了...
I broke the...
查克  查克
Chuck? Chuck!
查克  緊急呼叫
Chuck? Code blue!
查克  你能聽見嗎
Chuck, can you hear me?
他食管裡有血
He's got blood in his esophagus.
靜脈曲張出血
He's got a variceal bleed.
開一袋生理鹽水  交叉配型四個單位
All right. Saline wide open. Type and cross four units.
我要包紮靜脈
I'm going to band the vein.
血壓上升了
Pressure's coming up.
-查克靜脈曲張出血  -我也在場
- Chuck had a variceal bleed. - I was in there.
門脈高壓  代償失調
Portal hypertension, decompensated...
你說完了嗎
Are you finished?
他可能只剩三個月了
He's got three months to live, maybe.
他得禁酒六個月
You have to be six-months alcohol free
才有資格登記
before you're registry eligible.
你還說自己數學不好呢
And you said you weren't good at math.
他得不到這個肝源就必死無疑
He gets this one or he dies.
存活倒數計時
你知道在早上八點警車有多快嗎
You know what this thing looks like at 8:00 A.M.?
我每天早上上班都需要警車護送
I need a police escort to work every  morning.
所有道路都在
280 South.
280號公路南段匯聚
Where are all roads meet.
聖何塞
不對
No, they don't!
-他怎麼了  -他有自閉症  警官
- What's wrong with him? - He's autistic, officer.
那是什麼意思
What's that mean?
他需要去醫院嗎
Does he need to be in a hospital?
他最不該待的地方就是醫院
The last place he should be is a hospital.
你在做什麼
What are you doing?
肖恩
Shaun?
你在想什麼
What are you thinking?
好吧  我不是在問你問題
Okay, this isn't a question.
我只是  我不知道你在找什麼  肖恩
I just...I don't know what you're looking for, Shaun.
我可以感覺到  它變得更緊實了
Yes, I can feel it. It's firmer.
然後呢
And?
我不知道那是什麼意思
I don't know what that means.
這裡面肯定有凝塊  但我找不到
There must be a clot, but there isn't a clot.
片子裡看不到有凝塊
The scan showed no clot.
那是因為片子是在
That's because the scans were taken before
摘除肝臟之前拍的
they harvested the liver.
那時肝臟還沒有被UW液沖洗
Prior to the liver being flushed with UW solution!
它要死了
It's dying!
為了保存肝臟  他們把裡面的血液
To preserve the liver, they replace all its blood
全部替換為防止肝臟被凍傷的溶液
with a solution to protect it from the cold storage,
但裡面肯定殘留了血液  形成了凝塊
but they must've left some blood behind, which clotted.
離聖文德醫院還有多遠
How long to St. Bonaventure?
-不到三十分鐘  -來不及了
- Less than 30 minutes. - Can't wait!
我們必須馬上清除凝塊  沖洗左肝葉
We have to immediately remove the clot and flush the left lobe
防止肝臟凍傷
to protect it from the ice bath.
必須馬上停車
We need to stop the car.
-在這裡嗎  -對  對
- Here? - Yes. Yes.
我們必須馬上在這進行操作
We need to operate right here, right now.
從右邊進行沖洗
Flush this from the right.
左肝葉
So, the left lobe,
從肝中靜脈開始
starting at the middle hepatic vein.
沿著鐮狀韌帶的切口侵入性更低
Less intrusive cut would be along the falciform ligament
從這可以進入第三段
to allow access to Segment III.
等你找到了堵塞點  我來負責清除
When you locate the blockage, I'm gonna have to remove it.
我需要一根吸管來做靜脈插管
I need a straw to cannulate the vein, please.
我杯子裡有根吸管
There's a straw in my cup.
UW溶液可以穩定細胞壁
UW solution will stabilize the cell walls.
保護器官的完整性
Preserve the integrity of the organ.
這比在我車裡生孩子還厲害
This is better than having a baby in my car.
你感覺怎麼樣
How are you feeling?
像在開空頭支票
Like I'm writing a blank check.
你會沒事的
You're gonna be fine.
你是最好的醫生
You're the best.
出血  靜脈曲張  這些都不是好現象
This bleed, these varices -- this isn't good news.
這意味著你的肝衰竭進一步惡化了
Tells us that your liver failure has progressed considerably.
有多嚴重
How much?
你還能活兩到三個月
You have two to three months.
我們今天就有肝源了  一個小時後
We're getting - the liver today, in an hour.
我不明白你在說什麼
I don't get it.
你沒告訴她們
You didn't tell them.
什麼
What?
你父親喝酒了
Your father had a drink.
他就喝了一杯
He had one glass.
移植登記中心不會管你喝了多少
Transplant registry doesn't quantify things like that.
所以他得不到這個肝源了嗎
So he doesn't get the liver?
我會試著幫他爭取
I'm gonna try and get it for him.
你是汽車銷售員嗎
What are you, a car salesman?
你會試一試
What, you're gonna try?
最終決定不由我做主
The final decision is out of my hands.
如果你失敗了呢
And if you fail?
我會竭盡全力
I'm gonna do everything that I can.
十分鐘後我會與委員會的人碰面
I am meeting with - the committee in 10 minutes.
失陪了
Excuse me.
BGM: American Honey by Lady Antebellum
那杯酒是我遞給我父親的
I handed my dad the drink.
事情經過不重要
Doesn't matter how it happened.
他不想喝的  他只是想讓我開心
He didn't want it. He just wanted to make me happy.
如果他死了  那就是我的錯
If you let him die, I will have killed my father.
他只喝了一杯
It was a glass.
在他女兒的畢業典禮上喝了一杯香檳
A glass of champagne at his daughter's graduation.
化驗結果可以證明
I have the labs to prove it.
查克沒有酒癮復發
Chuck didn't fall off the wagon.
他只喝了一杯  僅此而已
He had one drink and never went back.
移植登記中心的嚴格規定
The transplant registry guidelines don't play
是有原因的
in the gray for a reason.
那些規定太專制了
Those guidelines are so arbitrary.
只是喝一杯酒就被剝奪生存的希望
Have one drink and you die.
吃搖頭丸卻沒問題
A couple pills of ecstasy, no problem.
隨意的性行為導致的B型肝炎也沒事
Hepatitis B from careless sexual practice, nope.
對這些事都沒有規定
Nothing at all about that.
所以你想我們怎麼做  無視規則嗎
So, what do you want us to do? Throw out the rules?
我希望我們能不完全被這些規則所制肘
I want us not to hide behind them.
我們肩負著責任
We do have a responsibility.
沒有規則的話  那我們就得扮演上帝
Without the rules, we're playing God.
我們需要規則
We need the rules.
它會讓你晚上睡得更好嗎
Does that help you sleep better at night?
會
Yes, it does.
全州有800人需要今天這個肝源
We have one liver today, and 800 people in this state need it.
我不想對另外799人心懷愧疚
I don't want to be haunted by the other 799.
你的病人自己丟掉了這個機會
Your guy hasn't earned it.
他知道規則  這...
He knew the rules, and this...
這是一個技術性細節
it's a technicality.
不對  這杯酒才是一個技術性細節
No, the drink is a technicality.
潔西卡  這裡面涉及什麼法律責任
Jessica, what's the legal burden here?
十分重大
Significant.
如果我們執意要做這個移植
If we move forward with this transplant,
可能會導致我們失去在移植中心的特權
we could lose privileges from the registry.
-如果被發現的話  -如果被發現
-If it were discovered. -If it were discovered?
你是有多狹隘
How narrow can you be about this?
格拉斯曼醫生  你怎麼看
Dr. Glassman, where are you on this?
兩邊都有理
I can make a good argument either way.
請繼續
Go ahead, please.
最好將這些爭論都解決掉
Better to remove - the arguments all together.
他到底在說什麼
What the hell is he talking about?
我是說  我們醫院有個患者
All I'm talking about is that we have a patient
需要肝源
in this hospital who needs a liver.
我們也恰好有一個肝臟需要一個患者
We also just happen to have a liver that needs a patient.
沒那麼簡單
It's not that simple.
如果你為患者考慮  就這麼簡單
It is that simple if you consider the patient.
規則是次要的
Rules are secondary.
但是救助這個患者值得我們冒險嗎
But is saving this patient worth the risk
救了他就不能救剩下的幾百個
of not being able - to save hundreds of others?
我現在沒有幾百個患者
I don't have hundreds of patients right now.
我只有一個  他叫查克
I have one, and his name is Chuck.
血壓穩定
Blood pressure's steady.
供體血管到面動脈
Donor vessel to the facial artery,
準備縫合
and we're ready to close him up.
10-0縫合線  血管鉗
10-0 polypropylene and vascular forceps.
做得好  安德魯斯醫生
Nice work, Dr. Andrews.
這是什麼
What do we have here?
血腫
hematoma?
我看見了  找一找來源吧
I can see that. Let's find its source.
紗布棒  探針
Sponge, stick, and probe.
不是受體動脈
It's not my recipient artery.
心率在下降
Heart rate is dropping.
不管是什麼  都在壓迫他的頸動脈
Whatever it is, - it's compressing his carotid.
我沒辦法深入進去  需要更好的
I can't get deep enough here. I need better access.
我們從外面到三段
We move through zone three from the outside.
三段是雷區
Zone three's a minefield.
我知道  但是我們必須這樣做
I'm aware, but we need to do this.
不管你做什麼  趕緊
Whatever you're gonna do, do it quick.
裡面的東西正威脅著他
It's strangling him from the inside.
叫梅倫德斯過來
Get me Melendez.
存活倒數計時
我們做到了
We made it!
是啊  我們到了
Yeah, we're here.
下樓  來吧
Downstairs, coming up.
不不不  傑瑞德  你肯定不信
No, no, no. Jared, you're not gonna believe wh--
啊
Yeah?
知道了
Got it.
查克被放在了名單最後
Chuck's been moved to the bottom of the list.
聖何塞長老會醫院正過來取肝源
San Jose Presbyterian are coming to get the liver.
-血氧飽和度下降  -給他升到100%氧氣
-Oxygen sats tanking. -Up him to 100 % O2.
你得從裡面穿過下頜
You have to go through the mandible from the inside
來探測來源  只能這樣
to probe for the source. It's the only way.
手術放大鏡
Loupes.
我們必須小心  否則他可能會中風
We have to be careful in there, or he'll get a stroke.
我們只需要小心就可以了
We'll just have to be careful then.
給梅倫德斯醫生  下頜通道牽開器
Give Dr. Melendez - the mandibular channel retractor
還有五號骨刀
and number five bone cutter.
五號骨刀
number five bone cutter.
29分鐘  存活時間
29 minutes. That's a lifetime.
謝謝  真是了不起
Thank you. This is amazing.
要走了  整個團隊都在等著
Got to go. The whole team is waiting.
他叫奧利佛
His name is Oliver.
真是美好的一天
It was a good day.
我們拯救了一條生命
We saved a life...
只不過不是查克的
just not Chuck's.
BGM: Build It Better by Aron Wright
♪ You can still see where the water was ♪
♪ In a line at the top of the chimney bricks ♪
不是你的錯
It's not your fault.
我也想相信
I want to believe that.
♪ Can never be fixed ♪
♪ So, we saved a few things that were spared ♪
♪ And brought it to the ground ♪
♪ 'Cause you always build it better the second time around ♪
你好
Hello.
你在實驗室工作嗎還是什麼
Are you a lab guy or something?
-我是個外科醫生  -那太瘋狂了
- I'm a surgeon. - That's insane.
我能要回我的電池嗎
May I have my batteries back?
你借的那些
The ones you borrowed.
好啊
Yeah.
♪ You can still see where the water was ♪
給你
There you go.
♪ In a line at the top of the chimney bricks ♪
你叫什麼名字
What's your name?
我叫莉亞
I'm Lea.
我是肖恩·莫菲醫生  很高興認識你
I'm Dr. Shaun Murphy. Nice to meet you.
♪ Can never be fixed ♪
♪ So, we saved a few things that were spared ♪
♪ And brought it to the ground ♪
♪ 'Cause you always build it better the second time around ♪
♪ I drove past the place where we used to live ♪
♪ Where you said you never wanted kids ♪
♪ Sometimes, something so broken can never be fixed ♪
你今晚就跟我待在一起
You'll stay with me tonight.
明天  我們再解決其他事
And tomorrow, - we'll figure out the rest.
♪ You always build it better ♪
♪ You always build it better the second time around ♪